Guide to the Walter R. Roberts Papers, 1945-2016 MS2384.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Walter R. Roberts Papers
1945-2016
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Gregory, Bruce
Roberts, Walter R., 1916-2014
MS2384.UA
11.25 Linear Feet 9 Records Center Cartons
Dr. Walter R. Roberts (1916-2014) was a diplomat and a foreign policy and public affairs expert with a distinguished career in the U.S. Foreign Service and the former U.S. Information Agency. Dr. Roberts taught at George Washington University for over 10 years, and he was a co-founder of George Washington University's Public Diplomacy Institute, (later renamed the Institute for Public Diplomacy and Global Communication). His collection contains materials from his diplomatic work, his time on Executive Director of the Panel on International Information, Education and Cultural Relations ("Stanton Panel"), and his work at GWU.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection were received from Bruce Gregory in 2019.
Biographical / Historical
Walter R. Roberts (1916-2014) was a gifted diplomat, international broadcaster, teacher, and scholar known especially for his contributions to the practice and understanding of US public diplomacy in the 20th century. He was one of the first American diplomats to realize that diplomacy had fundamentally changed when diplomats and other foreign affairs practitioners began, as a matter of course, to communicate with people in other countries as well as their governments. For more than 70 years, he played a leading role in the debates and activities that shaped the institutionalization, professional practice, and scholarly study of diplomacy's public dimension.
Roberts began his government service as a broadcaster with the Voice of America and then as a career diplomat, first in the Department of State and subsequently with the US Information Agency where he served in US embassies in Europe and senior headquarters positions in Washington, DC. After his retirement from the Foreign Service in 1973, he devoted more than four decades to a "second career" as a public diplomacy activist, teacher and scholar. He undertook leadership roles at Georgetown University's Center for Strategic and International Studies, the privately funded Panel on International Information, Education and Cultural Relations, the Board for International Broadcasting, the US Advisory Commission on Public Diplomacy, the nonprofit Public Diplomacy Foundation, and its successor the Public Diplomacy Council.
In the 1980s and 1990s, he taught courses on public diplomacy at George Washington University and in 2000 became a founder with others of the University's Public Diplomacy Institute, subsequently renamed the Institute for Public Diplomacy and Global Communication, cosponsored by the School of Media and Public Affairs and Elliott School of International Affairs.
Born in Austria on August 26, 1916, Roberts was a graduate of the University of Vienna. Following his escape from Austria in 1938, the year of its annexation by Germany, he traveled to the United Kingdom where he earned his M.Litt, and later his PhD, at Cambridge University. In 1940, he immigrated to the United States and worked as a research assistant at Harvard University Law School until 1942. He then joined the US government's Office of War Information serving as a researcher, analyst, writer, and German language broadcaster for the Voice of America from 1942-1950.
Roberts was assigned to the Department of State's Austria desk in 1950. There he strongly supported the Salzburg Seminar in American Studies, which had been created in 1947 to bring students and prominent scholars from across Europe and America together in a setting conducive to cultural and intellectual exchange. Now known as the Salzburg Global Seminar, it is a forum where more than 36,000 leaders from 170 countries have gathered in fulfillment of its mission to bridge divides, discuss global issues, and shape a better world. Roberts remained a lifelong champion of the Seminar, working to obtain funding from the Department and US Information Agency, serving on its Board of Directors from 1993-1997, and thereafter as a Salzburg Global Senior Fellow. In 2010, he was awarded the Salzburg Cup in recognition of his service to the Seminar and cross-cultural dialogue.
In 1953, he joined the newly created US Information Agency (USIA) as deputy area director for Europe. He was a member of the American delegation to the Austrian Treaty Talks in 1955 where he participated in negotiating the treaty that ended Austria's occupation and restored its independence. In 1960, he was assigned as Counselor for Public Affairs at the US Embassy in Belgrade where he served under US Ambassador George Kennan. In Belgrade he began a lifelong friendship with the Embassy's air attaché Brent Scowcroft, interacted with Yugoslav President Josip Broz Tito, and began the research that led to publication in 1973 of his acclaimed book Tito, Mihailovic and the Allies, 1941-1945. In 1966, he was USIA's diplomat-in-residence at Brown University. In 1967 the Agency assigned him to Geneva as Counselor for Public Affairs at the US Mission to the United Nations. He returned to Washington in 1969 where he served first as Deputy Associate Director (Policy and Research) and in 1971 as Deputy Director (Policy and Plans), then the senior career position in USIA.
Following his retirement from diplomatic service in 1973, Roberts was appointed Director of Diplomatic Studies at Georgetown University's Center for Strategic and International Studies (CSIS). There, in collaboration with CSIS Chairman David Abshire, Dean of Georgetown's School of Foreign Service Peter Krogh, and former CBS President Frank Stanton, he played a leading role in creating the Panel on International Information, Educational, and Cultural Affairs – a privately funded non-government group (known as the "Stanton Panel") – created by the US Advisory Commission on Information and US Advisory Commission on Educational and Cultural Affairs. Its purpose was to examine and make recommendations on the operations, structure, and future direction of US public diplomacy. Roberts served as the Panel's Executive Director and primary author of its report, International Information, Education and Cultural Relations: Recommendations for the Future, issued in 1975.
The report, which gave early traction to the term public diplomacy, was radical in its qssumptions, original in its recommendations, and consequential in its influence – both for what it achieved and did not achieve. It sparked a decade of widespread debate among diplomacy practitioners and policymakers, strong public opposition from USIA Director James Keogh, and numerous Congressional hearings. It remains a pivotal document in the institutionalization of the US government's public diplomacy in the 1970s and 1980s. Following release of the report, Roberts served from 1975-1985 as the Executive Director of the presidentially appointed Board for International Broadcasting, which had oversight responsibility for Radio Free Europe and Radio Liberty.
In 1982, Roberts collaborated with Frank Stanton and George Washington University President Lloyd Elliott to create a Center for International Communication, which was housed for two years in the University's Center for Sino-Soviet Studies in Gelman Library. In 1985, Roberts was appointed diplomat-in-residence by George Washington University's Elliott School of International Affairs where for the next ten years he taught courses on "Diplomacy in the Information Age." In 1991, President George H. W. Bush appointed him to the US Advisory Commission on Public Diplomacy, a bipartisan, presidentially appointed oversight panel legislated by Congress in 1948. President Bill Clinton re-appointed him to a second term in 1994. When his service ended in 1997, the Commission took the unprecedented step of continuing his participation as an informal advisor. Roberts was the first, and as of 2018, the only career diplomat to serve on the Commission. During these years and until the year of his death in 2014, he wrote numerous speeches, opinion columns, and scholarly articles on public diplomacy, international broadcasting, Austria, and the former Yugoslavia.
In 1997-1998, Roberts was a member of the CSIS Advisory Panel on Diplomacy in the information Age and participated in deliberations leading to publication of its report, "Reinventing Diplomacy in the Information Age." He was a member of the Council on Foreign Relations, where in 2002 he participated in writing the Council's Task Force Report, "Finding America's Voice: A Strategy for Reinvigorating U.S. Public Diplomacy." He was also a member of the Washington Institute of Foreign Affairs. He received the Distinguished Honor Award from USIA in 1974, and in 2009 he received the Voice of America's "Director's Special Recognition Award."
In 1996, Roberts joined the Public Diplomacy Foundation, a non-profit organization founded by retired diplomacy practitioners in 1988 (later renamed the Public Diplomacy Council) to support the advocacy, study, and practice of public diplomacy. In 2000, he was a co-founder of George Washington University's Public Diplomacy Institute, (later renamed the Institute for Public Diplomacy and Global Communication). The Institute was co-sponsored by GW's School of Media and Public Affairs, Elliott School of International Affairs, and the Public Diplomacy Council. In 2005, he created the Walter R. Roberts Endowment at George Washington University to advance excellence in the study and practice of public diplomacy through the Institute for Public Diplomacy and Global Communication. The Endowment supports annual Walter Roberts lectures, student awards, forums, and other Institute projects.
Walter Roberts and his wife Gisela were married in New York City on August 22, 1939. Four weeks later, the newlywed refugees, with Europe plunged into war, embarked on a US flagged ship for Southampton, so that Walter could begin his second year of graduate studies at Cambridge University. They had three sons, The Honorable Charles Roberts, Circuit Court Judge, Lawrence Roberts MD, and William M. Roberts MD MBA, Rear Admiral United States Navy (ret.). William Roberts and his wife Patricia serve as permanent members of George Washington University's Walter Roberts Endowment Board.
Walter Roberts died on June 29, 2014 in Washington, DC. A remembrance "Celebrating the Life of Walter Roberts (1916-2014)," hosted by the Roberts family, the Institute for Public Diplomacy and Global Communication, and the Walter Roberts Endowment Board, was held in the City View Room at George Washington University's Elliott School of International Affairs on November 22, 2014.
History written by Bruce Gregory, 2018.
Scope and Contents
The Walter R. Roberts papers are arranged in nine boxes. Boxes 1-6 contain papers originally in the possession of Walter Roberts and given by him to Bruce Gregory in 2006. Box 7 contains papers from the files of Bruce Gregory. They include copies of Roberts' speeches and articles, and papers documenting activities of the Public Diplomacy Council, Public Diplomacy Institute, Walter R. Roberts Endowment, and US Advisory Commission on Public Diplomacy during the years Roberts played a leading role in these organizations. Boxes 8-9 contain German language scripts of Walter Roberts' Voice of America broadcasts, 1948-1950, in the possession of Lawrence Roberts and made available for the collection in 2018.
Custodial History
Boxes 1-6 contain papers originally in the possession of Walter Roberts and given by him to Bruce Gregory in 2006. Box 7 contains papers from the files of Bruce Gregory. They include copies of Roberts' speeches and articles, and papers documenting activities of the Public Diplomacy Council, Public Diplomacy Institute, Walter R. Roberts Endowment, and US Advisory Commission on Public Diplomacy during the years Roberts played a leading role in these organizations. Boxes 8-9 contain German language scripts of Walter Roberts' Voice of America broadcasts, 1948-1950, in the possession of Lawrence Roberts and made available for the collection in 2018.
Other Finding Aids
A detailed finding aid that goes into more depth within the boxes and folders is available upon request. Please contact the Special Collections for access to this document.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged into three main sections, which follows along with much of Professor Roberts' work. The arrangement was done by the donor, and has not been changed.
Public policy; Diplomacy; Gregory, Bruce
- Stanton Panel, 1972-1978; MS2384 Series 1; 7.50 Linear Feet 6 records cartons
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains information on the Panel on International Information, Education, and Cultural Relations ("Stanton Panel"), both during the panel as well as how it was received.
  Arrangement
  This series is grouped generally by date.
  - Papers, 1953-1975; MS2384-UA Box 1; 1.25 Linear Feet 1 records carton (Box 1)
    Reports and congressional hearings on US international information, broadcasting, and educational and cultural exchange activities, 1953 -1975. These documents provided much of the historical context for his work as Executive Director of the Panel on International Information, Education and Cultural Relations ("Stanton Panel"), 1973-1975. The box also contains his papers relating to the Commission on the Organization of the Government for the Conduct of Foreign Policy ("Murphy Commission"), 1973-1975, and the Commission's final report. The Murphy Commission collaborated informally with the Stanton Panel and endorsed its final report.
  - Papers, 1973-1975; MS2384-UA Box 2; 1.25 Linear Feet 1 records carton (Box 2)
    This box contains correspondence between Frank Stanton, Walter Roberts, members of the Panel on International Information, Education and Cultural Relations (Stanton Panel), senior officials in the US Information Agency and Department of State, members of Congress, and prominent Americans interested in the structures and future direction of US public diplomacy. The collection includes internal working papers, report drafts, the Panel's correspondence name files, and reports by USIA Associate Director (Policy and Plans) Barbara White and US Comptroller General Elmer Staats that influenced the Stanton Panel's deliberations and reactions to its final report.
  - Papers, 1973-1975; MS2384-UA Box 3; 1.25 Linear Feet 1 records carton (Box 3)
    This box contains internal working papers of the Panel on International Information, Education and Cultural Relations (Stanton Panel). Included are correspondence, memoranda, notes, draft report sections, minutes of executive committee meetings, verbatim transcripts of plenary panel meetings, and draft chapters of the Panel's final report.
  - Papers, 1975-1978; MS2384-UA Box 4; 1.25 Linear Feet 1 records carton (Box 4)
    This box contains Stanton Panel papers relating to release of its report, "International Information Education and Cultural Relations: Recommendations for the Future," in 1975, widespread media and public reaction to the report, USIA Director James Keogh's critique of the report's organizational recommendations, Frank Stanton's analysis of Keogh's critique, Stanton's appearances before House and Senate Subcommittees in 1975, and the Panel's follow-up correspondence. Two years of debate on the Panel's recommendations led to lengthy Congressional hearings in 1977 on "Public Diplomacy and the Future," chaired in the House by Rep. Dante Fascell (D-FL), and hearings in the Senate chaired by Senator George McGovern (D-SD). The box contains correspondence, witness statements, and the published hearings as well as papers on the subsequent reorganization of USIA, renamed the International Communication Agency, by the Carter administration in 1977.
  - Papers, 1972-1977; MS2384-UA Box 5; 1.25 Linear Feet 1 records carton (Box 5)
    This box contains reports, correspondence, papers, statements of employee organizations and other background documents acquired by Walter Roberts during the Stanton Panel's deliberations in 1974-1975.
  - Papers, 1973-1975; MS2384-UA Box 6; 1.25 Linear Feet 1 records carton (Box 6)
    This box contains background papers collected by Walter Roberts during his two years as the Stanton Panel's Executive Director; the Stanton Panel's administrative files; three ring binders with alphabetized compilations of Stanton Report transmittal letters and replies; planning papers and foundation funding appeals for a Center for Strategic and International Studies project on public opinion and information control in the Soviet Union; a copy of Walter Roberts' book, Tito, Mihailovic and the Allies, 1941-1946, (Rutgers University Press, 1973), and correspondence relating its distribution and translation.
- Public Diplomacy, 1982-2016; MS2384 Series 2
  This series is specific to Roberts' work in public diplomacy outside of the Stanton Panel.
  - Public Diplomacy, 1982-2016; MS2384-UA Box 7; 1.25 Linear Feet 1 records carton (Box 7)
    This box contains speeches and articles published by Walter Roberts from the 1990s until the year of his death in 2014, documents relating to his participation in activities of the nonprofit Public Diplomacy Foundation and its successor, the Public Diplomacy Council, and documents relating to his association with George Washington University as a teacher, as a leader in establishing the University's Public Diplomacy Institute, renamed the Institute for Public Diplomacy and Global Communication, and as the founder of the University's Dr. Walter R. Roberts Endowment for the Public Diplomacy Institute. Included also are folders relating to his membership on the US Advisory Commission on Public Diplomacy, 1991-1997, a collection of his miscellaneous papers, a remembrance celebrating his life in November 2014.
- Voices of America, 1945-1950; MS2384 Series 3; 2.50 Linear Feet 2 records center cartons
  This series pertains to Professor Roberts' work in Voices of America. More information is listed at the box level.
  - Voices of America, 1945-1947; MS2384 Series 3; 1.25 Linear Feet 1 records carton (Box 8)
    This box contains German language scripts of Walter Roberts' Voice of America broadcasts, February 1945 – December 1947. Roberts broadcast his own shows several times each week for more than five years from VOA's Austrian broadcasting service. Dates, times, and subject titles for each broadcast are in English. Many show his editorial changes. Roberts kept these scripts with his personal papers. His family made them available in 2018 after his death.
  - Voices of America, 1948-1950; MS2384-UA Box 9; 1.25 Linear Feet 1 records carton (Box 9)
    This box contains German language scripts of Walter Roberts' Voice of America broadcasts, January 1948 – March 1950. Roberts broadcast his own shows several times each week for more than five years from VOA's Austrian broadcasting service. Dates, times, and subject titles for each broadcast are in English. Many show his editorial changes. Roberts kept these scripts with his personal papers. His family made them available in 2018 after his death.